Mr. Xu, the embroidery on your clothes
许郎君这身衣服的绣样
is truly exquisite.
还真是精妙呢
[Look at the peach blossom pattern,]
这领口处的桃花样
I wonder which fair lady
不知道是哪家小娘子
embroidered it for you?
给你绣上的呢
I'm surprised you would say that.
大人说笑了
Actually, I'm fond of peach blossoms,
只是许某喜欢桃花
[so I picked one with that embroidery.]
便定了桃花绣样的成衣
Oh, I see.
原来如此
No wonder it looks so familiar.
怪不得这么熟悉
So this embroidery pattern
原是这绣样
is the one I've seen
是我在成衣铺里
in a pre-made boutique.
看到过的
[This is indeed]
这确实是今年
[a trendy style this year.]
时兴的样式
If I recall correctly,
如果我没有记错的话
it has an outer garment.
这套成衣还有一件外衫
Why aren't you wearing it?
许郎君怎么不穿呢
I might have forgotten it in the rush.
许是今晚忙忘了
I can't remember where I left it.
我也忘记遗留在何处了
You seem to be quite busy tonight.
今夜许郎君确实忙乱
In chaos, errors are inevitable.
忙乱中难免出错嘛
Then what is this powder?
那这粉末
What could it be?
又是什么
[If I'm not mistaken,]
如果我没有闻错的话
this should be the fabled
这应该就是传说中的
mandrake fragrance.
曼陀罗香
[I...]
我
I've never heard
我从没听说过
of that.
什么曼陀罗香
I also don't know
我也不知道
how it ended up on me.
为什么会在我身上
[Please see the truth!]
大人 大人明察呀
[The abduction of Lady Du]
杜娘子被掳走一事
truly has nothing to do with me!
真的跟我没有关系
Really?
没有关系
Jing Lin!
景内卫
[Xu Jize,]
许己则
[this piece of garment]
这件衣服
was discovered by us on the way,
是我们在路上找到的
is it yours?
是你的吧
Are you trying
你是想说
to deny it?
这件外衫不是你的
In your escape, you panicked
你在逃跑的过程中
and discarded your outer garment,
慌乱将自己的外衫扔掉
not realizing that
却不知道
the silver thread on the collar
外衫领口上的银线
got caught on the inner.
勾住了你的内衫
You also forgot
你更忘了
that the inner pocket
你外衫的内袋里
still held the mandrake powder.
还留着你的曼陀罗香粉
[And this powder]
而这迷魂香
[has also remained on the inner garment.]
也残留在了你的内衫上
[Xu Jize,]
许己则
you used the powder to sedate the bride.
你是用迷香迷倒新娘
You're a repeat offender,
是惯犯
and the mastermind behind this.
你就是这绑架案的主谋
You even killed your accomplice!
还杀害了自己的同伙
No!
不
That's not true!
不是这样的
I didn't kill anyone!
我没有杀人
I didn't!
我真的没有杀人
Sir,
大人
I did use the powder,
我是用了迷香
'cause I was captivated by the bride.
我贪恋新娘的美色
[But...]
但是 但是大人
I really didn't kill anyone!
我真的没有杀人啊
Such a shameless person,
如此厚颜无耻之徒
not a single word of truth!
嘴里没有一句实话
Lady Yan,
颜令史
no need to waste words on him.
无须跟他多言
Here!
来人
Bring the finger press!
上夹棍
[Yes, sir!]
是
Mr Mo,
莫刺史
please allow me...
还容我
No, no!
不要 不要 不要
I confess.
大人
Listen to me!
我招 我招
I'm telling you everything, everything!
我全招 我全招
Then tell us what you did tonight
那就将你今晚所犯之事
in detail and truthfully!
一五一十如实招来
[I used to believe that]
我此前迂腐
jade-like
惟信
beauties are waiting for you in books.
书中自有颜如玉
[But after becoming a wedding attendant,]
可是做了傧相以后啊
I've come to realize
我突然发现
that those aren't crucial.
美人不用读书也能拥有
With just a whiff of mandrake fragrance,
一点点迷香
even the most secluded bride
那高庭大院里的新娘
can become my own object of delight.
就全能成为我的颜如玉
[Because these subtle words]
因为这些隐晦之词
[cannot be spoken,]
无法言语
I often succeed
所以我多半都能得手
and no one is able to speak out.
也无人出去言说
Then why did you set your sights
那你此次为何把目标
on Lady Du this time?
定在杜娘子的身上
I have no particular hobbies,
许某没有什么爱好
just a fondness for fair ladies.
就是喜欢美人
I have long heard of
杜娘子的美名
[her beauty.]
我早有耳闻
How could I possibly miss such an
我怎么会放过这种
opportunity to be with
与营州大美人
the renowned beauty of Yingzhou?
共处的机会呢
What's the name
你的同伙
of your accomplice,
也就是死者
the deceased, I mean,
他姓甚名谁
[and your connection to him?]
与你有什么渊源
He was just a petty criminal.
他就是个混混
All I know is that he goes by
我只知道他叫
the name scummy.
二赖皮
[He's an orphan]
无父无母
[and has served time in prison.]
打家劫舍还进过监牢
Long before the man in black showed up,
早在黑衣人来之前
you're already in a heated argument.
你们就已经在争吵了
What's that for?
在吵些什么
I decided to end the abduction,
我决定终止犯案
and bring Lady Du back.
把杜娘子送回去
Hey,
不行
I made a mistake.
我搞错了
Let her go.
把她放了吧
Be serious!
你开什么玩笑
The die is cast.
木已成舟
You have to go through with it!
你不干也得干
It's a mistake! We should let her go!
我说我搞错了把她放了
You...
你
[Suddenly, a noise came from a distance.]
谁知远处突然传来声响
I'll check over there.
我去那边看看
[I suspected someone was tailing us,]
我怀疑是有人跟踪
[so I the argument ended.]
便停止了争吵
[He's]
二赖皮呢
[tasked with keeping Lady Du]
负责给杜娘子
[in the well.]
放在窖井里
[I went to check the surrounding area.]
我负责去周边查看
[But I found nothing.]
什么也没有
[Maybe it's just a stray cat, I assume.]
可能是只野猫吧
Bro,
二赖皮
I didn't see anything,
没看到什么
just a feral cat in the bushes.
只是树丛里有只野猫
Perhaps it made the sound.
许是野猫发出的声响
[I was in complete shock,]
我都吓懵了
[fearing that the murderer would return]
我怕凶手回来
[and kill me as well,]
把我也杀了
[so I ran away.]
所以我就逃跑了
Xu Jize,
许己则
about the murderer
你所说的杀人真凶
you mentioned,
除了你之外
[is there any other witness who saw him?]
还有其他的人证吗
Then,
既然没有
how can you prove
你如何证明
that you didn't argue and that
你们不是一言不合
he wasn't killed by you?
内讧自相残杀
If I had to fight with him,
若是我跟二赖皮打斗
he'd definitely have had the upper hand.
他必定占尽上风
[What strength do I possess]
我有什么能力
[to manage to kill him?]
能杀死他呢
Sir,
大人
please see the truth...
明察啊
For his death,
二赖皮之死
[I'll conduct a thorough investigation]
本官自会明察
before a decision.
之后再做定夺
The evidence in Lady Du's case is solid.
杜娘子一案证据确凿
[Someone!]
来人
[Detain the convict Xu Jize!]
将犯人许己则收押
Yes, sir!
是
Move!
走
Hey, aren't you
怎么
gonna sleep after a whole night of fuss?
折腾一晚上还不休息啊
Is the fearless Lady Yan so
天不怕地不怕的颜令史
scared of sharing a bed with her husband?
就这么怕与为夫同床
I do want to sleep,
我倒是想休息
but as soon as I lie down, my mind
可这一躺下
is filled with thoughts of the case.
满脑子都是案子
It's resolved smoothly, but I
案子破得倒是顺利
can't shake the sense of hidden truths.
但总觉得有好多隐情
Smoothly?
顺利吗
I chased the suspect until midnight,
追凶追到半夜
and it took him a long time to confess.
他认罪又花了许久
And it's only after being tortured
最后是要用刑
he finally revealed everything.
才肯全盘托出
What I'm referring to
我指的
is not just the bride abduction case.
不单是劫持新娘案
Even though it's closed,
就算此案结了
with the kidnapper scummy dead,
可劫匪二赖皮死了
there's a new murder case to deal with.
案子上又多了新的命案
He's a mere thug.
二赖皮是打家劫舍之徒
Here in Yingzhou,
在营州城内
he must have had many personal grudges.
肯定有不少私仇
What kind of grudges
是怎样的私仇
would lead to such a convoluted plot,
要如此故弄玄虚
killing him and
杀了人之后
then removing his eyes?
还要把他的眼睛给取了
Was the appearance of the murderer
凶手的出现是巧合
a coincidence, or was it all premeditated?
还是早就铺演好的
It's difficult to figure out right now.
一时半会儿想不明白的
You should get some rest.
先休息
But I can't fall asleep.
说了我睡不着了
Among his friends and family,
二赖皮的亲朋好友里
the most probable suspect would be...
看上去最有可能的是
Since you're so energetic,
既然这么有精神
why not do something else?
不如干点别的事
You...
你
What are you up to?
你要干什么
You know,
自然是干一些
as your husband...
夫妻之间该干的事了
You...
你 你
Out of your mind?
你疯了吧
They dub me the White Death,
世人叫我白无常
my word is law,
说我一言九鼎
my oaths unwavering.
言出必行
Yet in your sight, my love,
怎么到了夫人这儿
I am merely a lunatic, huh?
为夫就成了疯子
What did you give me?
你给我吃了什么
Slumber Pill.
甜睡丸
It can help you fall asleep.
能助人快速入眠
Sweet dreams, my love.
夫人一会儿做个好梦吧
[My Lord.]
大阁领
A letter from Xiang'an.
襄安来信
Why is it so urgent?
什么信这么着急
The lady is just about to sleep,
夫人刚要休息
and I haven't let you in yet.
还没让你进来呢
Apologies.
大阁领恕罪
But as asked, I have to
只是大阁领吩咐过
report such letters instantly.
此人来信要速报
An urgent letter from Xiang'an?
襄安急信
Who sent it?
是谁寄来的
Lady Xu.
徐内司
There's nothing discreet about it.
没什么好稀奇的
Would you read it first, my love?
不然夫人先看
Nope,
别别别
I'm not interested in your love letters.
你们的情信我不想看
I'm gonna sleep.
我困了 要睡了
Lady Xu and I are not
我与徐内司之间
romantically involved!
并无男女之情
Besides, the one I care about
况且本阁领在意之人
is someone else.
另有其人
Yan Xing?
颜幸
It really takes effect at the right time.
药效来得可真是时候
[We are Masked Specters.]
我们是半面鬼
[When are you going to find my head?]
你何时找到我的头
[Hand over your head!]
把你的头给我吧
[Who's there?]
谁在那儿
[Who is it?]
是谁
[Show yourself now!]
你给我出来
[My eyes...]
眼睛
[My eyes!]
我的眼睛
No!
不要
Is this...
这是
a red-feathered gray pigeon?
红羽灰鸽
[The arrival of this pigeon]
红羽灰鸽飞至
[indicates that there are]
说明这营州城内
[definitely undercover agents]
定是也有
[from Her Highness in Yingzhou]
太皇太后的探子
[who cannot show themselves.]
不便露面
[The pigeon is a signal]
用这灰鸽提醒我
[that I should report to the capital.]
该回报皇城了
Xing!
姐姐
Did you bring this gray pigeon?
这灰鸽是你带来的
Are you...
你就是
No,
不是啊
I just saw it hovering
我是看这红羽灰鸽
in your courtyard,
进了姐姐的院子
refusing to leave.
徘徊不肯走
Have you
姐姐
heard of the legend?
你知道那个传说吗
If a red-feathered gray pigeon
如果红羽灰鸽
makes its home at your place,
在你家安家
it means you will have great fortune.
那代表你要交好运了
You must keep it.
必须留下来
So I hurried to the street
所以我就赶紧去大街上
to buy you a birdcage.
给姐姐买了个鸟笼
Is that so?
这样啊
So you came
那你来
to bring me the cage?
就是给我送鸟笼的
There's one more thing.
还有一事
We've run out of deer antlers.
药材单上的鹿茸用完了
However, Gannan is low on herb reserves.
可甘南道地区药材匮乏
I've checked in the largest healing house,
我去了城内最大的医馆
Guangchun Hall.
广春堂
But they said they've never stored
都说没进过
such a rare item.
鹿茸这种稀缺货
They only have Cistanche.
他们只有肉苁蓉
It may need to be sourced from elsewhere.
可能得从别的地方调了
Cistanche, huh?
有肉苁蓉
Although it's somewhat inferior,
这个药效虽然欠些
it can still serve as a substitute.
但也能替代着用
The shopkeeper
掌柜的说
agreed to sell me the last bit,
最后一点卖给我
but I haven't placed the order yet.
我还没要呢
Take me there.
你带我去
Let's go get some now.
我们这就去买
Alright.
好
- Let's go.
走 走
Easy, easy.
慢点慢点
Big healing houses are indeed thriving.
这大医馆的生意果然好
Even the pots for decoction
连熬药的罐子
have to be custom-made this large.
都得定制这么大的
They shouldn't be for decoction,
应该不是熬药的
but rather for storing herbs.
倒像是储存药材的
By the way, Yeyun, I asked you
对了 野云
to keep an eye on the provincial office
之前让你注意刺史府
for any suspicious individuals.
有没有可疑人物出入
Have you found anyone?
你可有发现
Sis, your instructions are something
姐姐交代的事情
I have definitely taken to heart.
我齐野云肯定放在心上
I haven't spotted anyone for now,
可疑人物暂时没有发现
but I did learn about
但我倒是打听出了
a suspicious place.
一个可疑的地方
I've heard there's an inner chamber
听说刺史府有一个偏院
that no one is allowed to enter,
是谁都不许进的
yet Lord Mo frequently visits it himself.
但莫刺史自己却常常去
[Yingzhou is a harsh and frigid place,]
营州这边塞苦寒之地
[but it boasts such vibrant peonies.]
竟有如此盛放的牡丹
[Pink peonies?]
粉色牡丹
Lord Shen, this way please.
大阁领 这边请
Very well.
好
What brings him here?
他来这里做什么
Yingzhou's situated in the northern cold region.
营州地处北寒
It often experiences snowfall in winter.
冬日时常有雪
To have such a warm room to nurture flowers
能有这样一间暖屋养花
must have required considerable effort.
想来是花了不少精力的
Qianzhi.
师兄
Lord Shen.
大阁领
Do you have to distance yourself
师兄一定要与我
from me?
这么生分吗
In this day and age,
现如今
your position is quite significant.
大阁领的身份非同一般
I have experienced the trials
下官领略过
and tribulations of officialdom.
官场的水深火热
I simply wish to live a stable life and
只想安稳度日
have no desire to climb the social ladder
不想再攀上关系
or create difficulties for you.
令大阁领难做
I hope you can understand.
还望大阁领恕罪
In public,
在众人前
I understand your reluctance
你不想与我有所关联
to be associated with me.
这我可以理解
But now it's just the two of us.
但现在只有你我二人
Do you truly wish to keep me
师兄要拒阿渡
at a distance?
于千里之外吗
Back then,
当年
you were imprisoned
你被充入罪容所
and endured great suffering.
受尽了苦楚
In the end,
归根究底
it's the politics of officialdom
还是官场的是非
that have entangled you.
牵连了你
So from that moment on,
所以从那时起
I wished to keep
我便不想
you away from any
你与官场
further ties to officialdom.
再有任何的关联
But I never anticipated
可未曾想
that your exceptional talent
你天赋异禀
would still draw
兜兜转转
the attention of Her Highness.
还是入了太皇太后的眼
Now, you hold the position
现如今
of the commander of Imperial Guard,
你是大阁领
while I,
下官
can only remain a lower ranking official.
便只能是下官
I see.
我明白了
So you're blaming me, Qianzhi.
师兄这是在怪我呀
Exceptional talent?
什么天赋异禀
Drawing attention?
什么入了太皇太后的眼
The old acquaintances of the Shen Family,
沈府旧人
my father's old friends,
家父旧友
who doesn't know that
谁人不知 谁人不晓
I relied on selling my father for status,
我沈渡靠的是卖父求荣
and forced my own mother to her death
逼死了生身母亲
just to escape punishment.
才脱得罪籍
[I hereby report!]
我检举
[The traitor Shen Bingzhu's son, Shen Du]
罪臣沈秉烛之子沈渡
[accuses my father]
检举我父
Such despicable behavior
如此畜生行径
is something everyone can scorn.
人人皆可鄙夷之
Especially you, Qianzhi.
特别是师兄你
You must feel a deep regret.
师兄你一定很后悔吧
Back then, on the path of the palace,
当年在御街之上
you knelt all the way to the palace
一路跪行至皇宫
to plead for Shen Family...
替我沈家上书求情
[Your Majesty!]
圣上
[Lord Shen has been wronged!]
沈侍郎冤枉
[The Shens' women and children are innocent!]
沈家妇孺何辜
The late emperor spared us,
先帝念在师兄忠心
considering your loyalty, thus avoiding
才免去了
the death penalty for my mother and me.
我和母亲的死刑
And I was able to enter the Custodial Ward.
而我才得以入了罪容所
There's no need
此事
to dwell on this.
不必挂怀
My family has fallen into decline,
我家道中落
but fortunately, master (Lord Shen) took me in.
幸得老师收留
He has shown immense kindness to us Mos,
他对我们莫家恩重如山
treating me like his own son.
待我更是尤如半子
Pleading before the late emperor
御前喊冤
is my responsibility.
乃是我分内之事
If I were to neglect this,
若是不管不顾
that would be disloyal and unjust.
那才是不忠不义
You sacrificed a promising future,
师兄舍弃了大好前途
exiled here with no hope for promotion,
被发配边塞 升迁无望
just to save a disloyal, unjust,
只换得我这么个
and unfilial person like me,
不忠不义不孝之徒
merely to survive.
苟且偷生
Using my father's reputation
用父亲声誉
to barter for my own bright future.
去换自己的大好仕途
Qianzhi,
师兄
if you had known it would come to this,
若早知有今日
would you have regretted it?
你可曾后悔
Looking back,
回首过去
I have many regrets,
我有过许多后悔之事
but saving you
但唯独救你
has never been one!
从未
What you did that day
你当日所做
was an act of desperation.
乃是无奈之举
Master in heaven
老师在天之灵
will surely understand.
也定会谅解
"Your mother
所谓师母
angrily driving you out of the house"
大怒之下逐你出家门
was merely a show
不过是为了
to deceive those petty ones.
给那些小人看的
It was just a distraction.
障眼法而已
What she truly wanted
为的
was to protect her only son.
是保全她唯一的儿子
Qianzhi,
师兄
do you really not blame me?
当真不怪我
Do you recognize this flower?
你认得这花吗
I do.
认得
It's Xiuxiu's favorite flower, Tongzimian.
是绣绣最爱的童子面
[Where are we going?]
去哪儿啊
[Hurry up!]
快点快点
[Look,]
你看
[Du has some real skills.]
还是阿渡哥哥厉害
[He helped me raised Tongzimian.]
是他帮我种出了童子面
[Du,]
阿渡
[you're about to]
莫绣绣
[spoil Mo Xiuxiu completely.]
就快被你给宠坏了
[Tongzimian is rare to grow,]
这童子面
[with dozens of peonies]
数十朵牡丹里
[not necessarily yielding one.]
都未必能种出一朵
[Other young ladies]
别的小娘子
[would be satisfied]
头上别朵牡丹
[with just one peony on their head,]
就了不得了
[but you]
就你
[insist on a Tongzimian.]
还非要别童子面
[What's wrong with that?]
怎么了
[I just love it.]
我就爱童子面
[Du,]
阿渡哥哥
[the one on my head]
我头上这朵
[will soon wither in a few days.]
过几日便要谢了
[When it comes to that,]
到时
[remember to get the best one for me.]
你记得剪枝最好的给我
[Rest assured,]
放心
[I've already selected one.]
我已看好了一枝
[I'll pluck for you in a few days.]
过几日正好剪给你
After Xiuxiu passed away,
绣绣走了之后
I created this courtyard
我为她搭了
filled with peonies in her memory.
这满是牡丹的小院
Only then did I truly understand
才知道
how challenging it was for you
当年你为了种出
to cultivate
那童子面
that Tongzimian.
有多么地不容易
Du,
阿渡
how could I ever hold grudges against you?
我怎么会怪你
I can only feel gratitude
我只会庆幸
that you managed to adapt
庆幸你可以审时度势
and live well.
好好地活下来
So in this world,
这世上
there could be one more person like me
才能多一个像我这般
who cherishes Xiuxiu
爱惜绣绣
and keeps her memory alive.
记得绣绣的人
Life is indeed unpredictable.
世事无常
I never imagined that
我也没有想到
our farewell in the capital would turn out
当年在皇城一别
to be my final goodbye to Xiuxiu.
竟然是我与绣绣的永别
If Xiuxiu were still alive,
绣绣如果还活着
she would be
应当也是
about the same age as Lady Du now.
杜娘子的年纪了
Qianzhi, there's something
师兄
I've always hesitated to ask.
有件事我一直不敢问
How did she die?
绣绣是怎么死的
It was my failure to care for her.
是我没有照顾好她
She fell ill due to the
水土不服
unfamiliar environment.
病逝
[Xiuxiu?]
绣绣
[I remember now,]
我想起来了
[the rattan pig and the letter]
那藤编小猪和信笺
[were gifts from Mo Xiuxiu.]
是莫绣绣送他的礼物
[That's why he has kept them for so long.]
他才保存了这么久
Mo Xiuxiu,
莫绣绣
what are you writing?
你这写的是什么
Sir,
夫子
you frightened them.
你吓到她们了
It's nothing, nothing.
无事无事
Everyone, please continue your practice.
大家继续练字
It seems these children
看来这些孩子
haven't yet moved on
还没有走出
from the trauma of being kidnapped.
被绑架的阴影啊
Du,
阿渡
go collect some bulrushes.
你去找一些蒲草来
Sure!
好
Sir.
夫子
My lord.
老爷
Let's conclude
今日的课业
today's lesson here.
就上到这儿吧
Understood.
是
Children,
孩子们
in a moment,
一会儿啊
I will teach you how to
我要用蒲草
weave small animals with the bulrushes.
教你们编小动物
Does that sound good?
好不好
Yes!
好
Du,
沈哥哥
am I doing this correctly?
你看我这么编对不对
could you help me get started?
你帮我起个头嘛
You're so talented!
你好厉害
I want to weave one for Du
我也想编个给阿渡哥哥
as a birthday gift.
当生辰礼物
Can we trade?
能不能和我换一下
Of course, take it!
好 你拿去吧
Thank you!
谢谢
What's your name?
你叫什么名字
You can just call me Xing.
你就叫我六娘好了
[Because that was a gift]
因为这是莫绣绣
[from Mo Xiuxiu,]
送给他的礼物
[that's why he's treasured it for so long.]
他才保存了这么久
[It turns out the one he truly loves]
原来他钟情的人
[is Mo Xiuxiu.]
是莫绣绣
Today,
你今日
you asked to meet in private.
定要与我私下相会
What is it about?
究竟所为何事
The Shen Family has suffered injustice,
沈家蒙冤
and you're well aware of the details.
师兄是知情者
I was still quite young back then,
当年我年纪尚幼
and many things remain unclear to me.
很多事情记不分明
I hope you can share the details with me.
还望师兄细细与我说说
Lord Shen,
大阁领
it's all in the past.
事情已经过去
After so many years,
这么多年了
You have achieved great success,
你现在功成名就
with a bright future ahead of you.
前途无量
Don't let the past weigh you down.
莫要在意前尘旧事
What do you mean by that?
师兄这是何意
The suffering of imprisonment is something
充入罪容所之苦
that ordinary people cannot bear.
非常人所能忍受
Du,
阿渡
now that you're free,
既然出来了
don't dwell on seeking revenge.
不要想着寻仇的事情
Du does not seek revenge.
阿渡不为寻仇
But I'm a member of the Shen Family.
但身为沈家人
We deserve the truth.
沈家需要一个真相
You are now highly trusted
你现在深得
by Her Highness.
太皇太后的信任
As long as you maintain your stability,
只要安稳度日
your future is boundless.
前程不可限量
Do you truly have the courage
你当真有勇气
to give up everything
放弃现在
you currently possess?
所拥有的一切吗
If you want to thoroughly investigate it,
如果要彻查旧案
you must be prepared to give up
必定要推翻
everything you have now.
现在所拥有的一切
Do you believe
你觉得
it's worth it?
值得吗
Throughout history, those who can
古往今来
investigate and overturn old cases
能够翻查旧案的人
are often those without vulnerabilities.
都是没有软肋的
Now that you're married,
现下你已成家
can you truly disregard everything,
你当真可以不管不顾
burn your bridges,
破釜沉舟
and act solely for your own sake?
只为自己一人
I still maintain my stance:
我还是那句话
let's not revisit
旧事
the past any further.
勿要再提了
Lord Shen,
大阁领
the answer you seek
你要的答案
has already been provided to you.
下官已经给了
I hope you could
还望大阁领
think it through.
三思
[His relationship with Mo Qianzhi]
他和莫谦之的关系
[is indeed quite profound.]
确实很深
[But anyone can see that Mo Qianzhi]
但莫谦之任谁看
[is a principled official with integrity.]
也是两袖清风一城好官
[Alas, pigeon,]
鸽子啊鸽子
[how should I]
我该如何
[report to the Great Grandmother?]
向太皇太后汇报
My sweet master!
师父姐姐
Sweet master? Think again?
师父什么姐姐
What a naughty disciple!
为师怎么教的你
Follow some decorum when you enter!
你进门要守点规矩
I knew it!
我就说嘛
Sis got up early
我姐姐一大早
to prepare medicinal dishes.
就来熬药膳了
She is truly a remarkable wife!
世间哪有这样的好娘子
She deserves someone better!
谁能配得上
A lady like her
夫人这样的
is indeed rare in this world,
的确世间少有
and she is a perfect match for my lord.
与我家大阁领那是绝配
Truly a pair of ideal partners!
一对璧人
A pair of ideal partners, you say?
还一对璧人
You know,
不是我说
your Lord Shen
你家大阁领
certainly carries himself well in public.
在外确实威武
However, at home, can he really be
可回家就称不上
considered a good husband?
好夫君了吧
Unlike sis,
哪像我家姐姐
who is a top-notch detective in public,
出了厅堂是第一女神探
and a master chef at home!
入了厨房也是女德楷模
How can it be said that
怎么回了家
he's not a good husband at home?
就算不上好夫君了
Enough of that!
闭嘴
Do you need me for anything?
你俩有事吗
If not, please step outside.
没事就出去
I need some peace and quiet!
我想清净点
Yeah, I do.
有有有
I really do.
谁说我没事
I just wanted to ask
我是想问
how the deer antler and cistanche
这个鹿茸换了肉苁蓉
turned out.
熬出来的怎么样
Is it usable?
能用吗
After all, it's just a budget substitute.
毕竟只是廉价替代品
If it doesn't work,
不行的话
order Jing Lin
就让景内卫
to the neighboring county for supplies!
快马加鞭去邻县调吧
This is to prepare medicinal dishes
这可是给他家大阁领
for his Lord Shen.
熬药膳
He has to contribute as well.
他不上心怎么行
C'mon, stop saying that.
你别一口一个我家
You're also
你现在也是
being fed by the Imperial Guard, you know?
靠内卫府养着好吗
You also freeload on our daily training,
每日还蹭我们训练
and I'm forced
我还得被迫
to take you on as
收你这么一个
a less-than-stellar disciple!
不达标的徒弟
Jing Lin,
景内卫
I must convey this to you seriously.
我要严肃地告知你
The only master
我真正想拜的师父
I truly wish to have
有且只有一个
is right here in front of you,
就是你面前的
Scribe of the Ministry of Justice, Yan Xing.
颜幸颜令史
She's not accepting me at the moment,
只是她暂时不收我
so I've reluctantly allowed you to indulge
我才勉为其难
in your desire to play the role of a master.
让你过了当师父的瘾
Mind your tongue!
你好好说话
What do you mean
什么叫让我勉为其难
you're reluctant?
过一个当师父的瘾
You're the one who should mind the tongue!
是你没有好好说话
Do you think I want
你以为我愿意
to take you as my disciple?
收你这个徒弟吗
Speak to me with respect.
你好好跟我说话
Out, out, out!
出去出去出去
You need to clarify this!
你给我说清楚了
[Substitute.]
替代品
[Leaving home.]
背井离乡
[Reuniting with an old friend.]
再遇故人
[A lonely man and a lonely woman.]
孤男寡女
[A fleeting infatuation.]
一时移情
[Perhaps what I feel as ambiguous]
可能我所感受到的
[and enchanting]
暧昧旖旎
[is merely because I am seen as]
都是因为被当成了
[a substitute for Xiuxiu.]
绣绣的替代品
[Yan Xing,]
颜六娘
[do you have the luxury to dwell on this?]
你还有闲情想这个吗
Xing!
六娘
You mean that
你是说
Lord Mo has agreed
莫刺史答应了
to combine the bride abduction case
将劫持新娘案
with the decapitation case?
与无头尸案并案处理
Not a full consent,
也不是完全答应
but he allowed me to conduct a comparative
但他同意仵作
examination of the two bodies
在初步查验之后
following the coroner's
我可将两具尸身
preliminary check.
一起对比探查
At least there's a chance to combine the cases.
至少是有并案的可能
Do you want to join me in autopsy?
要不要一起去验个尸
Absolutely, let's go!
好 这就去
Sist, I'll grab the toolbox for you!
姐姐我帮你取工具箱
Sis, here.
姐姐 给
Let's head out.
走吧
Mind your step.
当心
They seem to have a lot to discuss.
姐姐好像和他很有话聊
My lady just feels you're too noisy!
夫人只是嫌你吵
You're noisy!
嫌你吵
You are even worse!
你更吵
You're the noisy one!
你才吵
So childish.
小孩
Wait a minute,
不对
we can't let them chat too much!
不能让他们太有话聊
Where are you off to?
你干吗去
Hmph, you're the childish one!
小孩
What are your thoughts
你对凶手的特征
on the murderer's characteristics?
有何想法
Not much to say,
无甚想法
but the whole Yingzhou is abuzz.
但整个营州城都传开了
Everyone is convinced that
每个人都言之凿凿道
the murderer is the notorious
说这凶手
masked specter
就是甘南道
from Gannan.
广为流传的半面鬼
They say the masked specter
说这半面鬼
only consumes
每次
one specific part of the body each time.
只吃人身上的一个部位
This indeed aligns with
这倒是跟前面两个案子
the previous two cases.
对上了
There're many ghost stories in the folklore.
民间多有鬼魅传言
While ordinary folks might believe them,
普通百姓信也就算了
you, the top detective,
你堂堂第一神探
do you also believe in ghosts?
也信鬼神
I don't believe in ghosts,
我不信鬼神之说
but I do respect legends.
我只是敬畏传言
Regardless of their origin,
无论这传言从何而起
the fact that they've spread across
能在全城传开
the city must have its reasons.
定有它的道理
There might be someone behind it, or
或是有高人藏身其中
it could reflect the local circumstances.
或是当地局势的映照
Do you remember
这个传言
how this rumor goes?
你还记得是怎么说的吗
The masked specter
半面鬼
strikes when the victim is unconscious,
趁人昏迷之后作案
and when the victim awakens,
被害者醒来之后
they find they're missing an arm or a leg.
才发现自己缺胳膊少腿
Exactly.
对
That's why all the cases
这就是为何
involving the masked specter
所有半面鬼食人案
are so difficult to investigate.
查不下去的原因
First,
第一
there's no immediate threat to life.
没有危害生命
Second,
第二
everyone fears ghosts,
人人敬畏鬼神
and the victims are terrified,
受害者心生恐惧
so they don't dare to cooperate,
又不敢配合
which ultimately leads to a dead end.
最后只能不了了之
Additionally,
还有
these two corpses...
这两具尸体
were alive when they were
都是活着
beheaded or had their eyes gouged out,
被人砍头或者挖眼
and the victims ultimately died.
且被害人最终死亡的
Either the murder
要么这凶手
is not the same masked specter,
不是之前的半面鬼
or he was trying to
要么凶手
imitate the masked specter but failed.
模仿半面鬼没有到位
Only Lady Yan has the audacity
也只有颜令史有这胆量
to not fear ghosts
不怕鬼神
and dare to join me
敢前来和我一起
in navigating this murky situation.
蹚这趟浑水了
A murderer
杀人凶手
is nothing to be afraid of.
有什么好敬畏的
Whether human or ghost,
管他是人是鬼
a killer must face the consequences.
杀人就该付出代价
Even if it's an evil spirit,
哪怕是恶鬼
it should be us
也该由我们
who judge in place of the King of Hell.
代替阎王来审判
You...
你
What's wrong?
怎么了
The corpse has bruises.
尸体上有磕碰伤
It likely fell into the well,
应该是掉入窖井
causing external injuries.
造成的外伤
There are no internal injuries.
无内伤
The cause of death was a
死亡原因
shattered heart, leading to instant death.
是震碎心脏瞬间死亡
The corpse shows signs of lividity
尸身有紫涨
and also signs of decay.
还有腐败痕迹
The shattered heart
心脏震碎
accelerated the decomposition process.
加速了尸体腐烂的速度
Inside his abdomen,
他的肚腹里面
it must now be a puddle of mush.
如今应该是一滩烂泥了
The marks from this wound are completely
这次的伤口痕迹
different from those on the headless corpse,
跟无头尸上的截然不同
more decisive and clean-cut.
更加果断利落
Did you find anything?
可有什么发现
I can't quite recall right now
我一时也想不起来
what kind of weapon caused this.
这是什么利器
But it's definitely not the kind of
但绝对不是
curved blade from the Western Regions
我们之前见到的
we encountered earlier.
那种西域弯刀
It seems more like a specially crafted one.
倒像是特制而成的
Are you suggesting it's a weapon
你是说
designed specifically for gouging eyes?
那种专门剜眼睛的武器
Seems like something like this.
大概是这种吧
But I can't be certain
但我也不确定
if such a thing truly exists.
世上究竟有没有此物
Brass knuckles?
指虎
That indeed exists!
真有此物
It's a weapon
这是专门
worn on the fingers,
佩戴在手指上的武器
sharp as a
锋利程度
knife or sword.
不亚于刀剑
However, this weapon is quite sinister,
只是这种武器太过阴损
and typically only those
平时只有
who practice dark arts would use it.
修习邪术之人才会用
Using such a thing
这种东西
on a petty thug
用在一个小混混身上
is something
这一点
we should reflect on deeply.
值得我们深思
In that case,
如此看来
this case has no direct connection
此案跟无头尸案
to the headless corpse case.
没有直接关联
But the killer not only committed murder,
但凶手杀了人
but also took the victim's eyes.
又取走了人家的眼睛
What could that possibly mean?
到底有什么用处
I have no idea.
我也不得而知
Come take a look over here.
你来看一下这边
There's definitely something amiss.
确实有些不对劲
There are some faint
这皮肤表层之上
blue marks on
有些若隐若现的
the surface of the skin.
蓝色痕迹
If you're feeling tired,
你要是觉得累的话
you can go back and rest.
就回去休息
Leave this to me.
这里交给我
I'm fine.
我没事
I just didn't get enough sleep last night,
我就是昨晚没有休息好
so I'm a bit unfocused.
精神有些不集中
You two...
你们
Last night...
昨天晚上
What's with you today?
你今日到底怎么了
[Were they fighting?]
是不是打架了
Lord Commander
这大阁领
is really keeping a close eye!
看得还真是紧
[She seems like an ordinary teenage girl,]
乍看是个寻常的小娘子
[but whenever there's an investigation,]
而每逢查案
[she can set aside all the]
就能将所有恐怖不适的
[horror and discomfort]
气味画面
[and immerse]
抛诸脑后
[herself completely.]
全身心投入其中
[Yan Xing,]
颜六娘
[is truly an extraordinary lady.]
真乃奇女子
Mr. Pan,
潘郎君
in this stench-filled morgue,
在这臭味弥漫的停尸房
you can still lose focus?
你还能走神
I'm truly impressed!
在下可真是佩服
Lose focus?
走神
What's on your mind?
你在想什么
Do you have any new insights
是对这尸身
about this corpse?
有什么新想法吗
Not really,
倒也不是
it's just that throughout my life,
只是从小到大
I've never encountered a woman
还从未见过像你这样
as meticulous and brave as you.
细心又勇敢的女子
Seeing you now,
今日一见
I'm truly in awe.
实属佩服
If you hate to share your real thoughts,
你不想说的话
you don't have to say anything.
可以不用说
There's no need to use
倒也不必用
such a forced excuse.
这么牵强的借口
By the way,
对了
before we arrived,
我们来之前
was the corpse handled by anyone?
尸体可曾被人处理过
As far as I know,
据我说知
the corpse hasn't been processed at all.
尸体没有经过其他处理
It's just that some preservative
只是这个伤口上
was applied to this wound.
涂了些防腐水
Jing Lin,
景林
could you please fetch some
麻烦你取一些
preservative for me?
防腐水过来
Come again?
什么
Let me.
我去吧
Yeah, you!
你去吧
What is this?
这是什么
[Humans with]
诸生笑
[short lifespans]
飞蛾扑火
[mock moths flying towards fire,]
竟不知身为蜉蝣
[unaware that they'll respawn]
朝生暮死不入轮回
[after being tempered]
飞蛾历火不死
[in the fire.]
轮回重生
It's the Fire Moth Sect again.
又是火蛾门
[Brothers are not like brothers,]
兄不似兄
[people are not like people.]
人不似人
[Disrespecting the fire moth]
不敬火蛾
[brings disaster from above.]
祸从天降
This is... madness!
这 这见鬼了
It's not madness.
不是见鬼了
There's a schemer at work.
是有奸人在捣鬼
How do you know
你怎知
to use preservative?
要用防腐水
My master told me
我之前听我师父提起过
that in the Western Regions,
西域寄送密信
rice soup would be used
写信人会以米汤
for writing on sheepskin.
写字在羊皮纸上
Once it dries,
待干透之后
the words will vanish without a trace.
字迹便会消散于无形
After the preservative
收信人收到之后
is applied
会再用防腐水
to the sheepskin,
涂于羊皮纸上
they will turn blue
字迹便会泛蓝
and reappear on it.
重新显现在羊皮纸上
I just checked.
刚刚我看过了
There're blue marks on the skin
这个断头处的皮肤
at the decapitation site as well.
也有蓝色痕迹
So I decided to try it.
我便试了一下
[Rape and plunder,]
奸淫抢掠
[death is no loss.]
死不足惜
[Disrespecting the fire moth]
不敬火蛾
[brings disaster from above.]
祸从天降
To preserve the corpse,
仵作为了保存尸体
the coroner would use preservative
都会用防腐水
to soak the wound.
来浸润断口伤口
They chose rice soup
特意用接触防腐水
that would make the handwriting visible
就会显色的米汤来写字
upon contact with preservative.
这就意味着
I would go
从一开始
so far as to say
对方就没想过
that they never intended
让这字迹保密
to keep the handwriting confidential,
甚至可以说是
even intentionally
对方是故意
allowing it to be seen.
想让我们亲眼看到
Actually,
这些人啊
they don't mind us linking
根本就不怕我们
the Fire Moth Sect
把火蛾门
with the masked specter.
和半面鬼联系到一起
This crime
这罪状
is like a boastful proclamation,
就像一纸张扬的炫耀
seemingly telling us
似乎在告诉我们
that the Fire Moth Sect
火蛾门在甘南道地区
has infiltrated Gannan
渗透之深
far beyond our imagination.
远超我们的想象
In our investigation,
我们在探案之中
every move we make
我们的一举一动
is under their watchful eye.
都在他们的监视之中
Disrespecting the fire moth
不敬火蛾
brings disaster from above.
祸从天降